this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello this is Kishore Bhatia
for software engineering radio today's
episode is about several s architecture
with Nate dagger nate is the CEO and
co-founder of stacker II the enterprise
server list operations console Nate was
previously a product manager at New
Relic where he launched New Relic
browser here and the data science
program at github as a technical product
manager Nate's most recent blogs about
serverless are published at stacker IO
slash blog welcome to software
engineering radio Nate thanks for sure
alright today we are going to talk about
server less will understand the
motivations for this computing model and
do a deep dive learning about server
less architecture development frameworks
and tools we'll also learn from Nate's
experience with server this paradigm
developing operations tools it's tackle
and find out various approaches
challenges in this practices for
architecting and buildings over this
applications so Nate before we dive into
what several s is I just like to you
know for our listeners understand a
contextual history of you know how did
we come here what is the you know the
distributed computing model that that
led to server les yeah absolutely so if
we step back in history of web
infrastructure let's say we go back you
know 20 or 30 years people used to buy
physical Hardware right by a server
they've installed in their closet
somebody's job was to actually plug the
wires in and if you got too much traffic
more traffic than the server could
handle the solution would be to buy a
bigger server so this is what we'd call
skill scaling vertically and this worked
it was a very simple model but it had
some challenges too first off there was
no flexibility in in scaling you had to
predict in advance how much traffic you
were going to have and by an
appropriately powerful server to handle
and if you hit a limit you had to make a
large capital purchase of a bigger
server which could be you know five or
tens of thousands of dollars as you know
companies got more sophisticated about
their infrastructure they did start to
add multiple servers and generally they
would load balanced traffic across
multiple servers this did give some
flexibility in terms of scaling but
still was a long-range planning activity
eventually about you know ten years ago
now the clouds started to emerge and
instead buying spending a big capital
expense up front to buy infrastructure
the model was that you could rent
infrastructure down to much more
granular levels so you can pick
different sizes of servers and you could
even rent them by the hour instead of
having to commit to them for the
lifetime of the server so this is a
model that you know predominantly has
been driven by Amazon AWS and four years
it's worked really well to change this
model that we thought have been terms of
vertical scaling cat bigger servers and
it switched to a more horizontal scaling
model where you could just add more
servers and you could scale them up and
down and ultimately what we were doing
here was we were increasing the
utilization rate of the servers so
instead of buying a big server that was
more capacity than you needed it you can
now scale up or scale down and that
worked well except that as applications
became more complex you can think of big
monolithic applications became harder
and harder to manage the underlying
infrastructure to coordinate with
application changes we wanted to make
improvements to applications more
quickly we wanted developers to be able
to ramp up on a software project more
easily so we started breaking apart
these giant monolithic applications into
micro services now these micro services
were much easier to develop because they
were smaller portions of functionality
it was quicker and easier for developer
to ramp up on it but it introduced this
problem of orchestration of now you're
managing multiple layers of complexity
when it comes to managing your
infrastructure and your
zatia nari so for example if that one
application is now a dozen microservices
you had to individually manage how each
of those services scaled that became
complex and so in the last five years or
so we introduced this idea of
orchestration now orchestration is just
the idea that individual services can be
scaled turned on turned off restarted
recovered flex up or down in terms of
capacity and those services can run atop
a cluster of compute resources so now
there's essentially two levels that you
can optimize on you can optimize the
underlying infrastructure the cluster of
services or you can optimize at the
application level the individual
resources available to each micro
service now this works well in terms of
managing utilization and it also helps
developer ship applications more quickly
but it introduces a large degree of
complexity you have more points where
you're managing scaling you have more
points where you're managing health and
so this became you know a job function
that requires some degree of
sophistication and what we're seeing
with Cerberus is that for a large
portion of the market that need for
orchestration while they have it they
have the need because they want to drive
efficient use of their infrastructure
they don't necessarily see that as a
business differentiator for their
organization they don't want to hire and
and develop a deep orchestration skill
set because that doesn't really help
their organization meet the
organization's goals and so instead they
look for other alternatives and what we
found was circle is is that they're able
to outsource that skill set outsource
the need for orchestration but Amazon or
or Microsoft or Google handle the
orchestration layer and instead let
their team focus on developing
applications and then managing the
health of the applications on top of
this new model of managed infrastructure
gotcha well that was pretty you know
pretty good detailed view on how we came
about say the the challenges of you know
managing applications and you know the
whole application stack with you know
operating systems libraries the app
environment and you talked about cost
there and the efficient utilization
aspect as well when you say outsource
the need for our consideration at this
point are you talking more about
infrastructure as a service
you know platform as a service can you
go a little bit deeper on that side yeah
so orchestration is is really it's a
it's an engineering you need you need to
you know keep all of these micro
services connected allow them to be
aware of each other understand that
since they're fundamentally running on
physical hardware hardware fails
occasionally so you need some level of
redundancy some level of healing to
happen on the underlying infrastructure
and so with orchestration what we've
done is we've got extracted away in a
sense we've abstracted the
infrastructure from the application so
that the application can run on a set of
shared resources that can self heal and
the application itself can now flex up
or down on top of that so what kind of
benefits does that you know entail for
you know for different you know
different aspects of applications are
you talking more about it becomes easier
to manage just writing code in deploying
those apps or is it more on the cost
side that that these developments have
happened yeah so there's changes to
every stage of the application lifecycle
from a developer standpoint it tends to
be easier to work with a micro service
than a monolithic application in picture
an application that has million lines of
code it can take a while to ramp up and
your understanding of how that
application works and every time you
make a change to that application
there's potentially a lot of impacts
unintentional that you don't realize
will happen to the rest of the
application it's very interconnected and
intertwined but as you start to break
that application on part into functional
units you know as
for services that allows a team to say
specialize on authentication or
specialize on you know a checkout system
for the e-commerce site or whatever it
is that allows them to ramp up very
quickly become an expert on that part of
the code and provides a clean interface
to the rest of the application typically
through something like an API gosh yeah
yep so more speed more functionality
that needs to be managed and maintained
independently of you know each other in
it when we talk about micro services
here right and so that's you know that's
on the development side of the house but
keep in mind
typically you develop an application
that may take you know weeks or months
and then you run that application for
years a big part of the application
lifecycle is you know maintaining its
availability and health while it's
running and serving customers and this
micro service model gives you another
layer that you can you can manage the
performance of the application you can
have some services that that grow more
quickly than others and you don't have
to scale everything linearly gotcha
right so when you talk about several s
are these trends you know we just we
just discussed you know scale
manageability cost utilization and also
the the concept of you know developing
applications that are at a speed as well
as at a you know I think a functionality
level where you know modules and into
individual services micro services are
more independent of each other when it
comes to the whole lifecycle where is
the actual trend you know driving this
is it is it more on the business side is
it is it you know technology that is
driving this adoption of a computing
model that is more cloud Riven and more
you know infrastructure abstract driven
yeah I mean I think it's fundamentally
both so from a business side every
business regardless of you know the
service that they deliver they're
fundamentally looking to ship products
more quickly they want to increase their
velocity they want to be able to create
more value and of course capture more
value from their customers
at the same time they want to manage
costs so they don't just want to throw
infrastructure at the problems in scale
up arbitrarily they want to be able to
ensure that they're maximizing their
utilization of the infrastructure that
they're paying for and they want to
balance that efficiency with of course
the risk that they might go down or have
an error or not some other way fail to
deliver their services but from an
engineering standpoint you know it's
somebody's job to develop these services
and if they're trying to meet an
organization's goal of developing and
releasing products more quickly they
have to look for ways where they're the
individual people on their team are able
to be more productive so microservices
offers a pattern for that where a
developer can ramp up on the team work
quickly without having to learn all of
the code base and you know of course
there are other patterns too we've seen
in the last five years the emergence of
containers as you know a pattern and
trend that people have moved towards and
that helps developers in at least at one
level helps developers maintain
consistency between their development
environment and production environments
and reduces the risk that as they're
releasing products and shipping things
more quickly that they're able to do
that safely and reliable as well and in
defining you know the the paradigm
itself when we say several lists we do
know that there are servers in server
less so how would you go about defining
that in in a way that it it you know
comes out technically strong but also
has you know a meaning for business you
know
development ops and security folks so
we'll just you know go down trying to
understand what is server less
absolutely so first off there's I think
a lot of debate around what is
serverless some people think of it as a
literal compute model maybe better
described as functions as a service this
is a code that you develop and will run
on demand in the infrastructure provider
I like to think of it more as a
development model where an organization
is able to take advantage of managed
services managed infrastructure and in
that way you know the focus
beyond the compute level of the
application but could with this
definition also touch on you know data
storage and API delivery you know other
aspects of the architecture being
fundamentally a managed provided service
by a cloud provider well you touched
about the definition being more
development centric and you say it's a
developing model how how would you break
that into you know various aspects of
development that that several s adds
into or makes it easier can you go down
a bit you know elaborating in you
mentioned API as you mentioned storage
you mentioned manageability how does
that make developing easier yeah so at
the end of the day developers have a lot
of aspects to the job when you look at
the entire software delivery lifecycle
so if you can focus and and specialize
on a single level of that lifecycle you
could potentially increase your
productivity pretty dramatically so for
example a developer might say you know
the way that I add the most value is to
focus on writing code focus on
developing the functionality and the
business logic of my application and
they may not feel particularly skilled
at managing the underlying
infrastructure configuring a network
properly is a very different skill set
than writing code and there are people
who specialize at each for small
organizations it can be challenging to
build a team that has all of the skill
sets required to manage the entire
lifecycle and so managed services a
shortcut to that problem but even for
large organizations I mean if you if
your business can focus on building
products and delivering products and
doesn't have to focus on you know
managing boilerplate infrastructure that
frankly you know Amazon or Microsoft can
do better than you anyway
there's potentially a competitive
advantage that you gain there where your
business is focused on building and
creating value and your competitors are
focused on managing boilerplate part
right that makes sense and that that
does that apply equally to as you
mentioned the small start-up scale teams
and and large organizations that already
have deep expertise in say data center
management or network database storage
management yes and keep in mind that
these businesses are they're always
changing they're always evolving
I think counter intuitively we've
actually seen enterprises embrace
serverless much more quickly than the
broad startup market and I think a big
component of that is just how much is at
stake I mean a large enterprise may be
spending millions of dollars a year on
infrastructure and they may have
thousands of Engineers writing and
developing products so if they can cut
you know manage their their
infrastructure costs even by 20 or 30
percent and many of them see even much
more significant savings that can be
pretty material on the other hand if
they can help developers ship
applications more quickly that can also
be really material in their business and
I think the headlines that we hear a lot
about was service or that it's so much
cheaper to use and I think there's truth
to that sometimes that drives businesses
to look at server lists but what I found
is that most businesses embracing server
lists are actually doing it because of
the velocity that adds to their team
they find that they're able to build and
release products much more quickly using
serverless infrastructure because they
have to do less work in planning and
managing for capacity scaling the
application making sure they have high
availability they can outsource that
functionality and instead focus on their
application and the health of the
application that's an interesting point
and I'd like to come back to the the
comparison you know you made on cheaper
versus your velocity of developing
applications but you know just earlier
doing the definition you said that there
are certain definitions out there they
also talk about the functions as a
service aspect of server less can you
define what you mean by functions here
functions of the service
and why is that relevant to serverless
yeah so I think there's a lot of design
patterns that people can embrace when
they switch to serverless infrastructure
one thing that's important to understand
is that there's very rarely a way to
lift and shift and what I mean by that
is it's difficult to take an existing
legacy application that's on traditional
infrastructure and simply move it to
service infrastructure almost always
require some form of redevelopment RER
connection now that said there's a few
different patterns emerging and how
people build applications for service
infrastructure now at a basic level you
can fundamentally build a lot of
applications very similarly to how
they're built today
say for example you put an API endpoint
and connect it to a function as a
service what that would do is as you got
a request to this API endpoint your code
would run and return a response now that
looks very much like kind of a
traditional infrastructure model there
are some minor changes for example that
function is not long-lived it will start
and stop and because of that there's no
state that will carry forward from one
transaction to another but still it's
fundamentally follows the request
response loop that many developers are
used to thinking in as a development
model function as a service though also
enables other types of development
models and I think the big one that we
see really gaining in popularity right
now is what's called an event driven
model in an adventure of a model you can
subscribe your your code your functions
to listen to certain event triggers and
respond when those triggers happen so as
an example you could listen for when as
a file uploaded into an object storage
bucket when a file gets uploaded I want
my code to run that's commonly used for
something like transcoding videos or
generating thumbnails so an image gets
uploaded like when my function sees that
event happen it will then generate a
thumbnail and
and output that to another location this
event driven model is is interesting
because it actually makes applications
be feel much more distributed for
example at an enterprise organization
you may have a team focused on marketing
functionality that's listening to events
that are generated from say the
e-commerce site as an example someone
puts an object in a cart and then
abandons the cart now you could write a
function that looks for when the this
event happens when there's this
condition in the data I want to run a
function that responds to that may be
for example trigger marketing email that
responds to cart abandonment and so in
this way we start to see not only is the
code itself distributed running on
multiple physical servers behind the
scenes but also the development model is
distributed you have different teams
relying on and potentially reacting to
both code and events that other teams
may be ultimately responsible for
managing that was a great example of you
know how event-driven models are being
used in in real functionality you know
you mentioned the the file upload use
case and that was actually you know
something where you don't have to have a
lot of state you know to worry about you
can actually you know put a function
behind that that does something based on
an event happening but more
interestingly you know this this other
model that you were talking about with
an e-commerce card for example you know
there's there's development of micro
services that is distributed and
deployed and scaled independently based
on you know which way you see the most
load coming in but what is more
interesting to me here and maybe we
should probably spend a couple minutes
here is how this also distributes the
the team's attention on you know follow
up business actions like you mentioned
marketing email should go out if the the
cart was abandoned how are you seeing
these decisions you know being made are
you saying that this is because we've
got new new ways of
doing event-driven designs you know more
and more creative ways of engaging a
customer is coming in yeah so I think
it's worth pausing here and also calling
out the fact that you know while
event-driven software development is
really you know may be much simpler with
a server list model this isn't the first
time we've we've developed enterprise
software that responds to distributed
events for years we've had you know
frameworks that incorporate some kind of
message bus which is in a you know in
fact an event-driven model and many
enterprises are used to developing in
this way I think the difference here is
that because these events are broadly
distributed developers can now build
applications that are also broadly
distributed and it makes it much easier
to manage if you know say functionality
that you develop becomes much more
popular use much more heavily than you
anticipated you can do that very safely
and very reliably with Cerberus
infrastructure and alternatively if it
becomes used maybe less than you're
anticipating your costs for running that
functionality will be relatively that
much lower because Cerberus generally
runs on a paper use type model so maybe
you mentioned the cost versus the
velocity on you know developing with
serverless models and then we did a
pretty good example on functions as a
service and again you know when we do a
deep dive we'll talk about what
functions are how do we develop them but
let's just go back to the cost here how
how do how does one measure the total
cost of ownership or the return on
investment for investing in a service
model and what is pushing that from a
cost perspective you know so maybe it's
worth stepping back again and looking at
the evolution of infrastructure and how
cost has changed in that time and I'm
going to talk about some numbers that I
think service general guidelines their
normative to what we see in the industry
but they may not be perfectly
representative of
every application so typically if you
look back when we scaled servers
vertically you had to expend a large
capital expenses might be tens of
thousands of dollars upfront to buy a
powerful large server and you did that
with in mind the maximum scale that you
would need over potentially a one-year
or multi-year lifespan of that server so
in this way you have relatively low
utilization rates you might have
utilization rates of only say five
percent of the capacity of that server
and what I mean by that is let's say as
an as an arbitrary example your server
is able to handle ten thousand requests
per minute you may typically on average
only see something like you know five
hundred requests per minute and in that
way you have a lot of capacity that's
available for peaks in traffic but that
means you've over provisioned most of
the time in the scale out model this was
the horizontal scaling that you could
get from say a cloud provider like AWS I
think a lot of times we would see that
companies could drive somewhat higher
utilization rate but still scaling out
could sometimes take several minutes and
depending on the complexity of the
release may be even longer than that and
so companies tended to look at scaling
in terms of how much would they need
over the course of say several hours and
while they might be quick to scale up
they would be potentially cautious to
scale back and so in this case is not
uncommon to see utilization rates of say
20% or 25% over the infrastructure when
we introduced containers and
orchestration we had now two ways that
we could scale so you could cluster
multiple servers together and create one
large compute cool of shared resources
and then we're on applications on top of
them because some applications may be
flexing up while others are flexing down
you could in theory drive even higher
utilization rates and
it's not uncommon to see a utilization
at 50 or even 60 percent on a model like
this as an industry standard I've heard
kind of a normal best practice would be
to scale up at somewhere between 60 and
70 percent capacity you want to add
another 10% of availability so with
numbers like that you would typically
not see utilization rates higher than 70
percent if you hit that level you would
of course scale up now a service in
theory you only pay for the time that
you're actually using and instead of
paying for infrastructure upfront by
buying it or paying for it by the hour
like on a cloud model you're now paying
for it by fraction of a second AWS lamda
meters throughput meters pricing based
on one tenth of a second intervals 100
milliseconds so you're getting much
closer to paying for what you're using
now in theory that means you're driving
a 100% utilization rate in practice
that's not really the case because
you're billed at 100 millisecond
intervals if you have a function that
takes 99 milliseconds to run you're
almost using exactly what you're paying
for on the other hand if you have a
function that takes 101 milliseconds to
run you pay for 200 milliseconds even
though you're only getting 101 and so
therefore you may still have lower
utilization rates than you might expect
from this kind of building model there's
an interesting dynamic here as well
which is that we're shifting the model
of who's responsible for planning and
managing infrastructure costs in a
cluster model or a cloud model or an
on-prem mooned infrastructure model you
have an Operations team or an
infrastructure team who's responsible
for capacity planning and then managing
the cost developers built applications
to take advantage of the resources that
are provided to them by the
infrastructure but
we've done here with server lessons
we've changed who's responsible for
infrastructure if developers write
functions that are highly efficient
infrastructure the application will run
faster and so therefore you'll be billed
for less infrastructure abuse on the
other hand if you write applications
that are less efficient you may in fact
be billed for more infrastructure for
the same level of functionality or
traffic now capacity is responsive to
applications instead of applications
being responsive to available capacity
so I think there's a big shift that's
happening here in the mindset of how we
think about infrastructure and
developing and managing cost yeah that's
a pretty interesting point you made
there about reversing the whole you know
capacity model to being proactively
scaling up or down based on the
applications and then also the fact that
you know and this this was actually
another question I had in mind
where are you saying that server less
means you know no operations at all or
more and more lesser operations going
forward and then you kind of highlight
at the point that you know here
developers are responsible for breaking
down these services into say various
function calls and the way they code
them the way they design them is now
responsible for what kind of capacity
utilization is is you know driven how
are you seeing you know different models
in the cloud providers you know we
definitely mentioned a tub with lambda
but are there other server less
infrastructure providers out there yeah
so there are in fact multiple providers
Amazon is leading the way today in
service although I say that Microsoft
has a well-developed offering and Google
also has a you know an offering although
I believe Google's is still officially
in beta in all three cases what we see
is that in general and the presents are
not picking a cloud based on a service
offering they're taking their service
compute functions to the cloud that
already has their data to the cloud
that already has their events to the
cloud that already has their you know
networks and authentications and that
they're used to deploying to and that
they already have skills developed for
that said I also want to step back and
talk about the operations point that you
mentioned I think service is high in the
hype cycle right now
you know Amazon has shown a lot of
growth in their lambda product they
feature it at reinvent the past couple
of years and I think we've seen
increasing investments from Amazon
Microsoft and Google in their cloud
service offerings and in response to
that I think we get a little bit swept
up in some of the the hype and some of
the you know excitement and buzz around
server list and just to break some of
that down wanting one of the trends that
I've heard discuss is this idea of no
ops that as a managed service there's no
operational responsibility for an
enterprise consuming service or function
as a service offering that is simply not
true
now there are parts of operations that
in fact do get outsourced to the cloud
provider availability is clearly
outsourced scaling is outsourced
orchestration is outsourced in a
serverless model but there's huge parts
of operations that are not being
outsourced so managing and maintaining
the health of the application that's
certainly not being outsourced how you
build and release an application with
automation and reliability that's not
being outsourced so I think if you if
you step back and you look at this you
know the application lifecycle if you
look at the DevOps responsibilities and
you say which ones of these are we
really getting rid of and which ones if
these are we still fundamentally owning
I think you'll find that there is a
significant amount of operations
responsibilities that still resides with
the company that's that's running these
applications so very true still seeing a
lot of the move from like you know the
previous operations that we used to have
for data centers and you know
infrastructure
moving into more and more of either
infrastructure at school or you know a
lot of focuses as you mentioned you know
getting into the automation pieces of
managing health proactively responding
to you know various events from a
self-healing perspective or or just
trying to make sure that there is more
and more focus on security as code you
know a pretty good you know point here
around just the containers being closer
to the the more micro services or nano
services like model there you can run
something stateless for a quick you know
single process in a container
you know manner and then you can
actually scale that on a cluster of
available
you know VMs how do you compare that
with with where several Isis and you
mentioned functions earlier so I'm just
trying to see if something like
containers as a service that a lot of
cloud providers now have like amazon has
ECS Google has its own kubernetes
Orchestrator for you know running these
containers in parts how does that match
up to where serverless is is that better
is it more like that is just one more
step closer to serve earnest yeah so
this is interesting because I think
we've seen over in particular over the
last six months the definition of server
list is starting to look more and more
like a gradient and very less much less
binary I don't think that there are
offerings that are you know purely
server lists and offerings that are
absolutely not server less and those are
the only two categories Amazon for
example recently released a product
called Fargate now farm a is
fundamentally a docker container that
you can run on demand so you develop
your application you put it in a docker
container just like you might run on top
of state kubernetes it's a instead of a
managing a kubernetes cluster you give
it to Amazon and running in a model that
looks very much like lambda so an event
can trigger this docker container to run
now with lambda in particular you have
some constraints on how long this
function can run for so at maximum
lambdas run today for 300 seconds I
think we might suspect that that that
number could change over time
but that's five minutes maximum run time
of five minutes so earlier we mentioned
a use case of say video transcoding well
if you have a small 30-second video clip
I think it's safe to say if you could
transcode it in 30 seconds but what if
you have a four hour video clip suddenly
you want something that can be
long-lived now that state may still be
transactional and it may still not have
you know multitrack transaction state
requirements and so in a case like that
far gate could potentially be a hybrid
solution it's not constrained to run in
only five minutes you can run the docker
container essentially as long as needed
I but it still looks very circumcised
it's event-driven it's stateless between
transactions and again you don't have to
manage the orchestration or the scaling
or the availability or the underlying
cluster that it's running on top of you
can also look at some other offerings
like you mentioned you know I managed
kubernetes Amazon released eks Google
has for for a while now how to manage
kubernetes and of course there are
companies like platform 9 that were on
real kubernetes with kind of a managed
service layer in each of these offerings
you see various levels of outsourcing
for the management of the underlying
infrastructure I think Amazon's model is
to give you you know the the big knobs
how do you scale and you know what are
your scaling rules what type of
infrastructure do you want it to run on
and then they try to abstract the actual
running of the kubernetes cluster as
much as possible or at least simplify
that management aspect and then there
are offerings of course where you're
running kubernetes natively and you're
managing all of the cluster and you're
managing all of the orchestration and
the service discovery and you know the
availability and the health of the
application and now you're looking at
something that very much does not look
super listed and does not look like a
managed service at all so Nate just
diving into the architectural aspects of
server nests what are the components of
server that's architecture yeah sure
that's a great question so
this is actually where you know we've
talked about this name functions as a
service as an alternative to circle us
and I think this is a point where that
name
starts to break down it places a lot of
focus on the compute side of the
architecture the function the code
running and in reality serverless
applications use diverse set of
architectural resources just like other
applications do at a basic level a
serverless application will typically
have at least three components so the
first component is some kind of event
trigger now that may be an API gateway
it may be an object store it may be you
know listening to say a queue or a
stream and then it's going to have the
compute component the function itself
with the code that runs this would be
something like a lambda or you know an
azure function and then it's also going
to have some kind of state management so
almost all our applications and
certainly not all but most applications
do in fact mean some kind of state and
since serverless
you know functions are stateless
typically what developers are doing is
that they're storing state and some
other service like for example a
database the traditional database or it
could be something like say dynamo DB or
amazon is now releasing something called
aurora serverless which is essentially a
sequel like database that doesn't
require you to manage the underlying
infrastructure so this is this looks
like I think a basic service
architecture you have say an API
endpoint connected to a function that
has access to a database but in reality
most service applications are even more
complex they may involve multiple event
sources they will frequently and will
involve multiple functions or compute
nodes and then they may of course use
multiple databases multiple types of
databases and other
resources like message Hughes event
streams network players you know all of
the compassion say all of the components
that you might use for traditional
architecture I think again the
difference in thinking here for service
is that as much as possible those become
managed services that a developer in
theory at least does not need to
configure or manage the scaling for this
is actually probably a good point to
also call out that functions in this
case is possibly an overloaded term
there is of course the ability to deploy
a function which is you know a small
granular piece of code that does one
discrete task and that's I think how
developers have used the word function
for the last couple of decades but in
this case this function as a service
this compute node can actually be
complex your function can have you know
requirements so you can use libraries
just like you might normally get the
function can also actually serve as a
full application you get on multiple
files you can have multiple functions
again we've overloaded that work so your
compute node could run an application
which itself in the code has multiple
functions you could even have some kind
of application router which said you
know say takes an event source and
figures out what kind of event it is and
then runs the correct code function to
serve that event and so in this way I
think we're also seeing a divergence of
patterns and over time this may
consolidate but there may in fact be
multiple use cases where one or the
other makes more sense for different
applications that's pretty interesting
as an architecture I come from the
service-oriented architecture world and
it's a it's it has been actually an
interesting view on how a lot of the
micro services architecture replicates
some of the concepts that you would you
would earlier do just that you know you
wouldn't have as commoditized with
cheaper computing power and the fact
that you would have G RPC and like
Jason's and you know more lightweight
ways of doing rest HTTP calls today
and that's why I think more and more
applications back then in the in the
early 2000s were we're communicating
with each other on the protocol level
differently being monolithic in its in
its own sense but I do have another
question on the architecture here where
is the the application
you know structure growing in in terms
of how do you actually accept traffic
from the outside so I'm just trying to
get into the load balancing aspect of it
or the scale aspect of it like how do
you how do you route traffic from from
amazon's you know internal external and
internal you know five or rules in both
balancers and then how do you deal with
storage when it comes to you know going
outside of just the database is it is it
all managed by the service provider or
do you still have to you know worry
about routing rules and and thinking
about you know database as a service and
ns3 and things like that yeah good
question and i'd say a complex question
because you know i don't want to
oversimplify and and act like there's
only one solution here I think in truth
there are you know as many architectures
as there are companies developing them
tightly that said there are some
patterns that are pretty typical
so a typical interface to the outside
world for a serverless application would
probably be an api gateway type of
service now amazon has in fact an api
gateway there also other API gateway
providers mash shapes calm is an example
of you know third party API gateway and
you know some companies could develop
their own API gateway and might actually
run on a server and just farm traffic to
service applications but they typically
though to be a traditional service
application you're probably looking to
couple manage services with your your
compute layer and in that way you know
Amazon's API gateway sitting in front of
a lambda starts to look like a pretty
typical model this load balancing aspect
is again typically not going to be an
actual
or software developer to deal with if
they're using a managed service product
so with AWS lambda or Microsoft hazard
functions Microsoft and Amazon are now
responsible for that availability that's
scaling that load balancing in the you
know the actual provisioning so think
about you've released an application has
an API gateway connected to say a lambda
that's the entire application you get
one request from that API gateway and
that lambda will behind-the-scenes run
on a server inside of Amazon's data
center now what happens if you start
getting multiple concurrent requests
well now that behind the scenes as an
implementation detail that lambda could
actually be running on multiple physical
servers and in fact as you scale it will
be you know queued up to run on even
more physical machines each one of them
running independently they don't share
state this is the part of server lists
were just stateless of course and there
are some other implementation details
that may may in fact matter in to how
you manage them on your application so
one of them is that each of those
services will create our servers so I
will create their own logs their own log
streams based on the transactions that
ran through that physical machine so in
this case if you're trying to look at
the logs say for a service application
instead of looking through a single you
know log stream or a single log file you
may in fact have to aggregate through
multiple log streams to find the
transaction you you're concerned with
another consideration is what are known
as cold starts so the first time that a
service function runs it will boot up
the actual runtime you can kind of think
of this like a micro container right and
I'll load that that instance in the
runtime and the code and depending on
the programming language that could take
anywhere from say half a second for you
know maybe a lightweight node
application to
several seconds or a heavier java
application once that application runs
it'll be cached and each subsequent call
to that function on that same machine
will run much more quickly it doesn't
have to reboot up the runtime so if you
have an application that scales up very
quickly its amazon's job or microsoft's
job to create that availability to
distribute your code and your function
on multiple machines but you may in fact
hit a scenario where because you're
scaling up quickly your function that's
being delivered on more and more
machines which are not warmed they're
not cached you could in fact hit a bunch
of cold starts and have your application
performance be degraded long term I
would expect that this is a concern for
server lists that will go away over time
and for many applications it's not even
an issue today if for example you're
running some kind of background tasks
this is not a customer facing solution
something that doesn't have real-time
needs these cold starts are you know
annoying
at worst right but if you're serving a
customer facing API and you know some
percentage of your traffic probably some
non-negligible percentage of your
traffic is hitting these these cold
boots it could potentially be a customer
facing performance issue that you would
want to be aware of and be addressing in
your architecture and your application
design this again can have implications
in how you actually architect the
application so remember we talked about
the model of having larger functions
that do you know multiple multiple means
multiple features if you run one lambda
that has in its code multiple functions
you you may in fact have a higher
probability of being able to keep that
lambda warm over the entire application
whereas if you decompose that into each
code function has its own lambda that it
runs in you have more chances of hitting
hitting cold cold starts and so I think
there are you know there are two things
that are happening here one is this
managed service does have some
implements
in detail so the developer should
probably be aware of and that could
impact the architecture and to the
technology itself is still evolving and
I would expect that this trend is you
know slowly addressed by the service
providers and will eventually become a
non-issue and for certain types of
applications may already be a non-issue
I see that was a pretty interesting take
on like you know a developer's
perspective of say architecting an
application in the surrealist model i
think you also cover it the the part
where some of the the cold starts you
know log streams for example how do you
actually get them how do you t bug
things there was another you know set of
questions around if I have to do you
know a deep dive on architecting a
surrealist application from the ground
up we're not even talking about you know
migrating or transforming something what
kind of approach you know have you seen
taken between a role that is more
developer centric versus are all that is
more say technology program manager or a
CIO CTO who's trying to do you know
buying and evaluating decisions ongoing
server less so let's take the the
developer first and then we go into the
you know the technology decision maker
roles and then evaluate the same
question in two different ways yeah so
one way that we can discuss this is how
companies are in fact choosing to use
serverless what that adoption pattern
looks like I think this is really
telling on on how those decisions are
made and how the different stakeholders
react and what drives them right in
every Enterprise company we've worked
with we've seen that serverless was
initially brought in by a single
developer or small development team we
call this the rogue developer one person
has a project that they need to ship and
they discover that it's quicker to do
this by shipping a lambda than it is by
having an architectural review meeting
and a provisioning meeting and planning
the capacity and you know building and
packaging up a container and then
ultimately provisioning it with the ops
team and
they say you know what I can bypass that
I could write my function you have it
running in an hour
and I'm just going to do that so from a
developer standpoint a lot of times
lambda can just be seen as a way to
circumvent a heavyweight infrastructure
process now there's a lot of truth to
that it is faster and easier to ship
code using lambda in a lot of cases but
there are some concerns based on what
the type of application is that's being
developed so if this is say a background
task which is what we typically see
these rogue developers starting with
it's not mission-critical
it's not customer facing maybe it has
low visibility in the organization
there's relatively low risk to try a new
development model and because they're
able to ship quickly and get a quick win
they may in fact be praised for making
this decision where they've introduced
the new technology that can grow to
other teams seeing the win and wanting
to replicate that pattern and serverless
kind of spreading throughout the
organization in this way it's kind of a
bottoms-up way of distributing the new
bitty model that said it can introduce
some challenges to the organization as a
whole and this is where we see say a
Director of Operations or AP of
engineering or in fact even SEO or CTO
getting involved as a stakeholder as
serverless proliferate through the
organization there are some concerns
that will emerge the use cases tend to
evolve the visibility races the
criticality of the application may in
fact rise and you know as more use cases
are discovered and more services applied
throughout the organization it becomes
increasingly important to standardize on
how these functions are being released
to register them somewhere so that you
have an inventory and you know what
functions are available and have been
developed to create policies around how
do we set up I am roles or permissions
what's the security model how do we
standardize our release process how do
we roll back how do we get our
visibility how do we recover
from a health crisis in the application
I think these are the standard questions
of a CIO or CTO it's going to ask of any
infrastructure in any application
throughout the organization
but what service a lot of these
questions have historically been hard to
answer and that's part of the reason why
you know I for example have focused our
company on surveying operations needs in
the service market it's a perspective
that I'd want to go down and trying to
understand the increasing importance and
maybe visibility into policies and
standard you know like standard
approaches and then a major part of that
is also security you know how do you
manage security and in a several s world
for both applications you know edge
security and then making sure that it's
not just you know feeling like it's
secure but it's actually secure but
we'll go down into that and in in the
next section you mentioned something
more about you know how this the small
visible you know low-risk application
can then slowly you know start becoming
more and more pollinated I'd say or you
know getting into the the visibility of
the the ops folks and then then folks
starts you know trying to understand how
do you standardize this for a larger
scale application development effort
when someone's try to do this from a
from an architecture perspective are
there still benefits or concerns that
are driving this adoption for a CIO like
trying to do a new transformation on
capacity scale availability you know all
those kind of abilities that several
assaults by default is there any you
know direct approach to someone saying
you know from the top down that we want
to go several layers let's just go start
doing that have you seen that kind of an
approach what is it more like we're
already as part of our cloud journey
doing some some of these things it
doesn't hurt to show some quick wins by
trying something new yeah we've
definitely seen two approaches to
adopting service the first and again the
most common by far is this bottom side
we have individual developers bringing
it in as a technology that enables them
to increase their velocity that said if
you read the headlines in the serverless
market you probably be inclined to think
that companies are saying let's cut our
infrastructure costs by switching to
surplus I haven't actually seen that in
the market every enterprise that we
talked to had a top-down approach to
service has fundamentally been driven by
some strategic need in the organization
these typically fall into three
categories either the company is looking
to move to the cloud and they're saying
if we're moving to the cloud what are
the cloud technologies that we should be
embracing for example if we have to read
architect our application or if we're
going to have to touch legacy code in
order to facilitate this move to the
cloud we might as well we have an
opportunity now to modernize the
application and take advantage of the
cutting-edge development model so we
might we we should embrace serverless
we should do it intentionally and we
should use our our migration to the
cloud as a driver for that the second
driver that we see is a move towards
DevOps a lot of organizations they've
been hearing about DevOps for a decade
and they've been slowly trending in a
more agile model but they've yet to
fully embrace the DevOps model
serverless I think natively enforces
DevOps as a model think about the idea
behind the DevOps that developers and
operations are interlinked that there's
a team responsible for managing the
entire lifecycle of the application what
was server less if you want for example
access to logs on the compute resource
you have to manage logging in advance
the serverless function will start up
run the code and then die off there's no
server to SSH into and retro actively
collect logs now this is a somewhat
trivial example but I think it
illustrates how the model is changing
developers have to be forward thinking
about what the operational needs are of
managing this application throughout its
lifecycle service in
is a DevOps pattern in the development
cycle and then carries through to the
operations side of the life cycle of the
application finally we see a trend
towards micro services a strategic goal
of moving to distributed at
architectures distributed applications
or micro service pattern being a driver
towards service if you're an
organization who's been managing
monolithic applications for years
possibly for decades you're probably
familiar with the fact that it's
difficult to onboard new engineers to
the team it takes them a while to ramp
up and become proficient in the codebase
because there's a lot to learn and it's
also difficult to manage that
application monolithic applications tend
to have higher infrastructure
requirements higher needs in terms of
capacity of resources and can be
difficult to scale granularly
and so there's a lot of good you know
compelling reasons from an engineering
side but also from a business side that
might steer and enterprise organization
towards embracing a micro service
development pattern now if you have a
monolithic application and you're saying
alright we're going to stop you know
extending the monolith and we're going
to start augmenting it with micro
services let's say we're going to take
one component of our application say
authentication we're going to break this
out of the monolith and we're going to
develop a micro service for this now you
go and you look at the the technology in
the market and you say what's the
easiest quickest way for us to ship this
this new micro service and you might be
drawn to service because it's a pretty
compelling offer you don't have to learn
kubernetes you don't have to manage
orchestration you don't have to develop
a team around scaling and availability
of this critical service while you're
also focused on breaking apart your
monolith and building the new service
and meanwhile this is not really new
functionality organisations developing
so you may be under pressure to deliver
this very quickly and get back to
building roadmap work and so these
drivers a lot of times will
dear CIO CTO VP of engineering a VP of
operations or infrastructure towards
intentionally embracing server lists and
pushing this pattern throughout the
organization that gives a broad view on
how technology management and you know
CI o--'s CEOs are looking at you know
adopting several s going down towards
the tool sets and you know the variety
of you know functions of the service
event-driven you know
models that are available does one
actually need as a developer say new
languages or system design coding
practices to take advantage of the
several espera dime or is it something
you can just start to jump in with
existing experience yeah that's a great
question
so I'd say service is relatively easy to
get started with in a in a hello world
kind of way there are a number of
frameworks that make it very easy to get
your first function up and running
they're also some really funny easy
projects that you can get started with a
great example would be to build
something like an Alexa skill let's the
skills actually run on lambda and so you
could build a small function you can
make a little game or have a tool that
you can extend your Alexa to do for you
and you could probably build that in a
day or a weekend and and get up and
running pretty quickly
that said once you extend beyond the
hello world functionality once you
decide you're going to build you know an
enterprise scale application or a
professional application as to run and
production has to meet you know
monitoring requirements and have some
reliability some health performance an
SLA suddenly lambda becomes a little
trickier and it does require a learning
curve for developers and for teams now
on a team that has multiple disciplines
say a team that has some some developers
and also some operations experts on the
team probably already in fact have the
skills as a team to to ship a server
this application and do it pretty
reliably that said if you're just a
developer and you're trying to build the
service
application there's probably going to be
a learning curve for you for example
let's say you're building your first
service application on Amazon and you're
going to do it at work this may be the
first time you've had to write
CloudFormation template this may be the
first time you've had to configure other
services in AWS again we talked about
what a basic service architecture looks
like it's not just lambda there are a
you know at some level there's an event
source there's probably some kind of
data store and then there's a bunch of
services that you probably want to be
using that aren't very obvious so for
example each one of those resources is
going to need IM roles permissions a
security model you're going to want to
apply you know CloudWatch logs and
metrics collection you're probably going
to want an instrument for some kind of
air visibility find a way to get health
metrics out of your application and find
a way to get diagnostics out if you have
a failure so that you can recover from
it and correct that problem so in this
way there is going to be a learning
curve it's not just write code and
you're good to go
and I think that's where the hype cycle
and the reality of serverless are
diverging today you will have to take an
operational look and there's some skills
you're going to want to develop as
you're doing that right that that sounds
like there's also a learning curve for
developers to start you know looking at
some of the cloud operations in cloud
services that are available prompt from
a service provider and in some sense you
know is it fair to say that if you're
looking at several less platforms and
programming in this model you would have
to also start understanding the the
complete ecosystem from the from the
cloud providers so for example you
mentioned AWS you know various services
we talked about I am you know even
sources data store you know API gateways
with that would that mean that as a
single developer trying to get a
holistic understanding of the server
less you know model I would have to
actually understand it abuses existing
services and then how do I make use of
some of the offerings like cloud
formation templates in and cloud watch
and and things like that yeah so I think
with a naive approach the answer is yes
we'll have to learn these other services
you will have to learn today
CloudFormation
or some other you know configuration
tool you are gonna have to learn some of
the implementation details in you know
how you configure a B PC or an epi
gateway or a data store that said I do
think there's another way to look at
this which is and this is something
developers have been doing for decades
and shouldn't be a new idea this is the
point of tools so if you're working in
an area which requires some some new
skills chances are someone has gone
before you figured out how to do that
develop some best practices and
incorporated those into you some kind of
tool a framework or platform in our case
you know we call it a console but it's a
way to standardize and take the
experience that others have developed
and incorporate that into your work kind
of in a plug-and-play kind of way I see
so that's more like a you know if you
can have like an abstraction of all of
these services under the under the hood
and have a toolset ready for for a
complete development platform
and that's actually something I want to
understand more from examples that you
have seen both in strategy and and you
know generally in the Savalas world what
are the some of the common tools for
designing architecting service
applications or like even from a
development world are there more like
IDE is that you have to go to or is it
just the same like lambda has its own
way of writing a function I can write it
in in Java or and then when it comes to
you know deploying it on say running it
on my local machine versus actually
trying to deploy that at a at a you know
testing or a production level how do I
go about doing that so just trying to
walk through the tool ecosystem in a
server less development model that's
great so really quickly let's start with
what does it look like if you don't have
tools so if you don't have tools and
just for consistency we'll talk about
that AWS environment so
so you don't have tools Amazon lambda
has four actually today now five
programming languages you can use you
can use Python node Java C sharp or go
so you pick one of the languages
whichever one you like and you write
your code pretty freeform there's not
really a way you have to write it or
structure it there is of course an input
value that you'll get from that event
that triggers it to run so you know you
should know what that object looks like
but once you get the event you can do
whatever you like with it so with again
without tools you'll log into AWS
console you'll copy and paste your code
into a form field it submit and you'll
have a lambda running now if you like to
use libraries which I think most
developers do you're going to find that
there is actually some packaging
requirements you have to download the
dependencies you're going to bundle up
your code you're going to create a zip
file don't want to upload that to AWS
it's a little more complex release
process and then again you're gonna have
to configure it to run based on the
reaction of some event so you're gonna
need to know how to setup at least one
other service and configure that in AWS
and again Alexa skill is a great way to
get started because Alexa will generate
the event there's an actual what's the
skills kit that kind of walks you
through this process and it will let you
focus mostly on just the code in the
lambda it's an easy entry point but
again now let's say we're breaking out
of this and we're gonna actually do this
professionally we need a more robust
architecture and we're going to start
applying tools to the process a lot of
companies will start with some kind of
tool there's typically some code
frameworks so apex service framework Sam
which is an Amazon framework are some
different ways that you can structure
your code and define your architecture
and release most of those will help you
with deployment at some some level the
difference here though is you know you
do get some level of abstraction
but once you break out beyond say a
function and beyond maybe an API
endpoint you'll probably have to start
writing the the rest of your
architecture in some version of
CloudFormation
now maybe rock CloudFormation it may be
you know slightly modified syntax but in
any event you're ultimately going to
have to learn how to describe your
architecture there are a few other tools
on the market that you may want to apply
to the problem so there are two leading
monitoring tools one of them is called
IO pipe that's a great tool it will give
you visibility into the performance of
your application and another one it's
called - bird and that will give you
some ability to collect some performance
and also I think it's it's more focus on
say debugging and testing so it might be
an early tool to try and then finally a
stacker in my company has an Operations
tool so a stacker you don't actually
write the confirmation you can drag and
drop your resources onto a canvas and
then we'll generate the CloudFormation
for you now you also want to think about
how do you actually release the
application so think about a built
pipeline you're gonna store your code
somewhere safe and github someway you're
gonna have to get it from github into
AWS now if you're using something like
Sam local or service framework or
staggering there's an actual build and
release process that they on if you're
doing it without tools though you're
probably stuck with copy and pasting and
if you're used to using other kinds of
tools in your architecture say terraform
or something like that you're probably
going to find that it's not well-suited
to managing server list specific
applications it's more general-purpose
so things like packaging up your
functions your libraries you may have to
develop your own process for a few years
back the companies that were getting
involved in circle is earliest and say
they developed a lot of this tooling
in-house but today most companies aren't
doing that they're looking through the
market they're finding what's going to
work best to meet their needs fit into
their workflow and they're bringing it
to life back into their their company to
again take advantage of what the
benefits of service are which is
velocity they don't want to build tools
they want to ship product and so they're
focusing on that with the team in
Christian countries there there's it
seems that there's an ever-growing list
of tools that are also adding into the
majority of serverless platforms yeah I
mean serverless as a market is only a
few years old at this point and I think
what we saw is a handful of companies
emerged in the last few years the
earliest ones were really focused on how
do I build applications if you think
about it that makes a lot of sense the
first problems that you're going to need
to solve is you're trying services how
do I build a service application and I
think what we're finding is that that
need is really shifting so companies
like stacker E and companies like IO
pipe have taken it from you know how do
I build an application to how do I
operate alas an application how do I run
it in production how do I get visibility
how do I get control how do I
standardize my release cycle how do I
integrated you to the rest of my team's
workflow and I think what we're gonna
find is over the next few years more and
more tooling will emerge that actually
focuses on running applications and
maintaining the health of applications
great examples there so we did cover
from a tool set example the development
lifecycle using service application you
know development languages for lambda
for example in the run time we also
looked at you know some of the options
to to actually look at monitoring and
performance I do want to like discuss
quickly about your views from from from
experiences you know doing it live it's
Thackery's platform how do you go about
debugging and testing something that
goes wrong both in the in in a
developer's local environment maybe with
a cloud and then also in in a test or a
production environment how do you
actually go about like debugging you
know or maybe even acting upon a upon a
monitoring event that just came in and
then you know trying to fix it yeah so I
will say you know I want to I want to
keep this from being too staff refocused
we used a curry to build stack rates or
another
and so I think our workflow might look a
little bit different than somebody who's
just getting into serverless the cloud
providers each have slightly different
models as well so let's kind of talk
look like without Twilley
for each cloud provider and then we can
go back and think about what does it
look like if you're using something like
I like Zachary or another tool cool so
Amazon has a specific position which
they they champion that you don't do
local development with serverless you
may in fact write your code locally but
you're running it in the cloud now
there's some advantages to this for one
you're actually running it in a real
production like environment so there
aren't any inconsistencies between
development and production at least in
theory
of course it comes with some
disadvantages to you write your code
takes a couple minutes to release that
into the cloud and that's you know if
you've gotten good at it and in that you
know in that time in those couple
minutes you know have kind of a break in
the site you may be had you know kind of
switch contacts a little bit and you
know it can be slow you have to make
change test it make a change test fit
and each time you have to wait a few
minutes can be a bit tricky still that
is the preferred model for Amazon it's
what they really champion and there are
some tools like Sam local that they're
releasing to try to make it a little bit
easier the problem with those tools is
that while it's true it may help you run
your lambda again these these
architectures are not just lambda
they're you know distributive platforms
that touch a bunch of different services
and it's impossible to replicate all of
EWTN mo running locally and you don't
have api gateway running locally and so
you get into a scenario where you know
you're maybe trying to you know mock up
stuff out some of these different
services and you're spending a lot of
time you know trying to recreate the
environment instead of just shipping it
to the cloud which is what amazon
champions now Microsoft and I will call
out that well I've used
as your functions I haven't used them as
extensively it's AWS but I will say that
Microsoft has a history of building
developer tools
you know Visual Studio and other IDs
that they they've released in in so
Microsoft I think takes a more developer
centric approach a less infrastructure
centric approach and they provide tools
that help you quickly test debug or on
applications and release them to the
cloud if you're just getting started
with service and you don't already use a
cloud I think it'd be perfectly
reasonable that you use you know at
first I think they have a great
development centric process that said if
you're already in AWS if you have data
there if you have other resources there
chances are it's not worth switching for
this and you should just go to where
your data exists so this is this is a
you know kind of a model if you if you
don't have tooling let's talk about if
you do have tooling so if you're using
something like say Sam Sam is specific
to AWS but it gives you a way to
structure your code gives you a way to
at least run Sam local and you know test
or run your your functions if you want
to do something like you know unit
testing that might be a good way to do
it but ultimately then you're going to
release and run it in the cloud to
connect it to all the other services
that it's working with if you're using
something like stacker II and now we're
getting into kind of how our team builds
stacker he manages multiple environments
as part of the way that works so we
integrate with your version control so
someone on our team will create a branch
and github they'll make their changes
they'll release that to their own
environment which is a kind of a sandbox
around their code in our shared AWS
account they're able to test it
potentially break it doesn't matter
because of sandbox they won't step on
anyone elses toes and when they're
satisfied that they you know their codes
ready they can they can merge that back
in go through the PR process when it's
merged into master
that'll trigger an automatic release
cycle which will not promote that new
master branch out into production and so
in this way we have kind of an automated
release cycle it doesn't require
developers to you know manually do
anything other than what they've already
done they can continue to use their same
IDs go through the same PR process from
a developer's standpoint very little
changes yeah that's a great overview of
the ecosystem that is available today
both without tooling and with tooling I
do want to get down into the security
aspects as we covered some of the things
before on you know how does one
developer go about creating a
surveillance application and then you
know we talked about operations aspect
of releasing it deploying it and the
monitoring alright what is the whole you
know services access control surface
areas for attack you know data isolation
what are those kind of concerns or even
like benefits that you have seen coming
in from several s and then we probably
would have questions around the whole
application architecture yeah so I'd say
your service security is becoming a more
and more prevalent topic and I think the
thinking around it is still emerging so
let me at least share my thoughts on the
topic but know that this is probably a
moving target today first off I think
some people would worry that the attack
surface on server list is relatively
large right your functions may be
running on any number of physical
machines that you don't have control
over and it can be difficult to enforce
a security model on you know n number of
machines that aren't yours that said I
would argue that the surface area for
service application is relatively
contained because there's no state and
each transaction is isolated in an
environment so it's impossible for me to
egress from my transaction to your
transaction so even in that case that
there there was you know certain types
of security vulnerabilities and I don't
think you know a service application
is immune to security vulnerabilities by
any sense but so it does it does isolate
some concerns because you have these
functions that are spinning up running a
transaction and then spinning down
shutting off another way to think about
you know security around Cerberus is in
terms of you know security policies
I am roles and permissions that can be
applied to these functions now I'd say
this is both a plus and a minus in the
way that serverless architectures work
on the one hand because you can
decompose your application into
individual functions you can create very
granular permission systems that isolate
a function into doing only what it's
supposed to do and in a case I would say
you know that's that's a great security
model instead of having to give a
machine access to everything that the
application is going to do you have a
single function access to only what that
function is going to do on the other
hand the human element kind of throws a
wrench into that security model if you
have a small team of operators maybe you
know working with security experts they
can control the policies on every single
application release pretty centrally
right but if you have hundreds of
developers that are creating
infrastructure changes as they change
code if those developers aren't thinking
about I am roles and permissions if
they're not consistently applying them
if they're not you know well-versed in
what the different permissions are and
how they work you do run a risk that on
you know as you have more cooks in the
kitchen you potentially can make a
mistake
or have gaps or leave something out the
last thing I'll say around security for
service is that because the
infrastructure model has changed because
you don't have access in the broad sense
to the underlying machines a lot of the
security tools that you might be using
things you may have purchased or you
know potentially even open source
projects no longer work so you might
find that you're you're looking for new
coverage or new ways to solve
security problems that previously you'd
already addressed so if you think for
example you know you're used to running
say some kind of demon on a machine
that's going to look for changes and
report those up somewhere you probably
can't run that anymore and so you may
have to just think about security from
fresh eyes and a fresh perspective if
you start moving to surplus one thing I
do want to call out if security is a
concern for your organization though is
that again early use cases for server
lists tend to be background tasks non
mission-critical work well visibility
work not very sensitive projects and so
in a case you might be able to start a
service build some competency build some
confidence and build your security model
that your policies your practices and
get that dialed in now so that as you
scale up as service spreads throughout
the organization standardized early on
what the right approaches and you're
you're being a little more
forward-looking in that way well it's a
great suggestion on also thinking about
building in some internal expertise and
capabilities with several s without
boiling down the ocean with say a large
you know ecommerce or like customer
facing application that has risks all
over so thanks for covering the various
topics around tooling operations you
know how does a developer go about
developing you know and and applying
several s applications made and it was
also good to know that there is an
evolving cart around you know security
we kind of discuss the hype around why
people think that serverless has more of
an edge security or attack surface
problem but you know there's also things
to look at from an access control data
isolation perspective comparing the
adoption space between startups and in
enterprises I'd like to now see if
you've got any views and learnings from
domains
you know verticals in the industry right
now as to what architectural patterns
are evolving and which one of those
verticals like you know IOT finance
healthcare are evolving with several US
models yeah so I thought
touch on this from a couple of different
directions first I know this may be
surprising a little counterintuitive but
we are seeing the general curve coming
from the enterprise Enterprise seems to
be leading the way in adoption of
serverless
and in particular it might not be the
enterprise's that you're thinking of
these are typically you know technology
focus bleeding edge technology doctors
in fact some of the earliest most public
adopters are coming from industries that
have historically been technology
laggards there are four industries that
we see really pioneering service and
those are media finance retail and
logistics think like shipping companies
so that doesn't we be kind of surprising
industries but if we step back and think
about how a server that's being used
what are some of the problems that it's
solving I think you can see why lagging
industries would be even more compelled
to adopt service first off those
industries probably haven't bet on
containers and orchestration huffily yet
so they're going from you know maybe a
model or two in older generations up to
the latest trend and they have a higher
ROI for making the switch the other of
course driver here is that there are use
cases that serverless does really well
tends to be great for very short-lived
transactional kinds of work and that is
exactly the kind of work that you know
finance companies face or retail
companies face so I think what we see
here is a trend towards you know improve
velocity embrace DevOps embrace micro
services but do it through a managed
interface managed service provider maybe
you know not have to build all of the
orchestration skills in-house and focus
on the use cases of the organization
that's driving a lot of these industries
one other thing I'd like to touch on
because I think it's a really
interesting fit and maybe is a little
bit more of a tech forward industry is
IOT use cases
so server lettuce has one really great
advantage which is that it scales up
very quickly and it's relatively
cost-efficient at any scale whether it's
scaled up or scaled down IOT really
relies on that kind of mechanic to
service the products life cycle as the
you know Internet connected device
connects to the backend and shares data
or downloads updates serverless is a
good fit for this and so we've seen some
of the leading adopters at circa lists
like iRobot the makers of Roomba their
big service adopters GE GE has a lot of
IOT devices that they're starting to bet
on service with and so what we see again
how the advantages of service apply not
just to the engineering problems but
also to the business's goals to managing
costs increasing velocity and being able
to adapt to any scale or unpredictable
scale serverless tends to be a fit in
those cases and that's what's driving
the adoption not necessarily companies
just trying to get onto the bleeding
edge of technology that's you a pretty
interesting take on there
and all the companies are applying that
indirectly jumping into several is even
if they had had like a long period of
data center driven you know development
practices chroma from a trend
perspective in maturity level where do
you see more and more platform providers
you know headed well you see more and
more in the future
very serverless computing generally in
in terms yeah so obviously serverless is
still early Amazon really WS lambda
about three years ago and while I point
to some examples of service models
existing prior to that I'd say that was
the first mainstream implementation of
what we think of today as serverless
that said in only three years microsoft
has matched Amazon Google has matched
Amazon iBM is betting on kind of an
open-source implementation there's a
number of companies that have developed
ways to run a function as a service type
Orchestrator
top of kubernetes so I think we're
actually seeing lots of evolution in the
technology very quickly now big part of
that is how quickly it's being adopted
when you have the technology that's
predominantly adopted by startups and
small businesses even if you get a large
number of companies to switch their
relative market size and scale means
there's still not a lot of money in the
market in this case it's being led by
enterprises and so I think when you have
that much money when you have enterprise
scale budgets flooding the market what
you see is that cloud providers like
Microsoft and Amazon are doubling down
and increasing their investments in this
space and then it's technology very very
quickly interesting where you know the
demand is coming from and and how that
helps enterprises actually again in
return you don't be better at doing
technology and what's your experience in
you know in in stock we as a platform
team itself like what are your learnings
would you would you be able to give us
some best practices that have been
helpful for your team yeah absolutely so
first off I think the model of who does
what is changing and you have to be
intentional about that so while for a
background task or for your first hello
world project it may not matter very
much if you have monitoring health
visibility if you have performance
checks if you have centralized logging
in order to get into production your
developers need to be responsible for
that and they need to know it and they
need to be trained how to do it right or
they needed to like stack rate that they
can standardize on that will do that
automatically for them in either event
you you want to make sure that the right
people know what their responsibilities
are on the new system the new way of
doing things so I would say that's
number one number two is that there are
certain engineering tasks that are
pretty easy to do and a long-lived you
know traditional server model that
actually become harder to do and serve
up this models and so it's important to
kind of rethink architecture designs and
and be willing to learn again and find
new ways of doing things
let me give you one quick example
serverless is well designed to scale out
very quickly so you have a queue of
events you could spin up a thousand
instances or a million instances to run
through that whole queue all at once a
synchronously so you can you can
complete a large amount of work very
quickly and then scale right back down
to zero once you complete that workload
and it doesn't cost any more to do that
so you might be tempted to use that
model very commonly but say for example
you're using a third party API you
probably don't want to a synchronously
hit that API with a million requests you
may have some kind of rate limit you
need to enforce these are some design
patterns that are actually harder to do
with serverless how do you meter and
slow down transaction volume now you may
not normally want to but there are going
to be times when that's an appropriate
pattern so coming with fresh eyes and
thinking about serverless
technology intentionally thinking about
what the implications are of how
serverless is actually implemented under
the scenes and taking advantage of the
parts that are extracted from you in the
parts that you know your service
provider will manage I don't think that
necessarily takes away the need to
understand how under the covers it's
working so be curious and try to learn
more about service if you if you start
embracing great now playing output and
what what are your best references for
learning more about sover less generally
as you you know as you see the the
trends of all yeah so if you're sure I
hope you can share some links with your
audience
Sam local is a great resource if you're
getting started on AWS and I'd also
recommend checking out a blog by a cloud
guru there our AWS and cloud provider
training consultancy does a lot of
working and collects a lot of the best
thinking around service it's a great
entry point if you're looking for
providers in the space I'd also check
out IO pipe their performance monitoring
will give you insight into how service
is actually working which I think will
help train your team and level up your
skill a lot more quickly great are you
available on Twitter LinkedIn that folks
can reach out like what's the best way
to reach out to you and your team
absolutely
so you can find us at stacker e dot IO
you can also check us out on Twitter or
stack or D IO and on medium we have a
blog called stacks on stacks that we
share the blog is also replicated on our
website so you can go to stacker io /
blog amazing I'll include all these
links and in communication handles
thanks so much Nate for spending some
time and giving us this deep knowledge
on one server lists also the ecosystem
and where things I've had it and you
know I will make sure that there is all
the links included any any last pointers
that you want to mention no thanks so
much for having me - sure and I hope
your audience has fun playing with
serverless technology thank you thanks
Nate thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC radio
slack calm you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening